Abraham: So how does an
organization decide what type
of cyber testing they should do?
This will depend on many different things.
Nicole: This may be related to
the size of the organization, the
experience of its IT department and
the nature of the business itself.
Abraham: A Pen test is best
used when an organisation wants
to focus on vulnerabilities
in a new system or project.
They are a more useful way to identify
specific vulnerabilities rather than
how they would respond to a real attack.
They can identify smaller
vulnerabilities that on their own
might seem insignificant in the scheme
of things, but these can be used by
attackers as an entry into a system.
Nicole: By following the
processes hackers do pen testers
can find these points of entry.
Pen testers will generate detailed reports
which meet the client’s specific needs
ranking and rating any vulnerabilities.
However, if a pen test is not done
correctly, it can cause damage by
crashing servers, exposing sensitive
data or even corrupt crucial data.
Therefore, it is imperative that
a pen tester can be trusted and
understands the needs of the
organization they are working for.
Abraham: Vulnerability scanning
is often used for checking systems
like web servers, VPN endpoints and
internet connections and as part of
the software development lifecycle.
It can help identify vulnerabilities
early as many attacks use bots to search
for and exploit known vulnerabilities.
Nicole: By using the same tools,
weaknesses can be discovered in
advance and if many vulnerabilities are
evident, it shows a system is flawed.
Automated scans save time and money
and can be repeated regularly.
By doing this an organization
can demonstrate they are meeting
standards and GDPR regulations.
Abraham: However, some vulnerabilities
will be missed as there are always
those that a scanner will not pick up
and it may bring up false positives
meaning that specialist help is
still needed to identify results.
Nicole: Red team testing is used
to create as near as possible
how real attackers would act.
It can’t replace vulnerability scans or
penetration tests, but is more useful
to see what would happen in the event
of a real attack and is a good way of
testing the ability of an IT security
team or Security Operations Centre to
detect particular types of attacks.
Abraham: However, it only usually
targets the vulnerability needed
to achieve the goal of the attack
and may not show all issues.
It can also involve the high
costs of using specialists.
Nicole: Social engineering
testing covers areas that the
other forms of testing don’t.
They are also very common forms of
attack, and many organisations will
fall foul of them at some time.
This form of testing helps the workforce
in understanding the part they play in
the vulnerability of their system both in
their personal life as well as at work.
However, this type of testing doesn’t
work in isolation and should be
combined with other forms of testing.
Abraham: Cyber security testing
is only part of the process of
safeguarding a system or network.
Once testing has been done this
should be followed up by mitigations
that respond to any risks that have
been identified during testing.
So, what exactly are mitigations?
Nicole: Mitigations are actions that
can help reduce the potential damage.
Let’s look at some of
these in more detail.
Abraham: If hackers gain entry to
a system, the threat needs to be
stopped before it can escalate.
Having a plan in place can help
with this by making critical
decisions such as taking a system
offline before damage escalates.
A mitigation plan can help with
identifying who has control
in these circumstances and can
make the appropriate decisions.
Early containment is key
in reducing any impact.
Nicole: This can be done by
performing regular updates and
patching any known vulnerabilities.
Keeping malware protection up to date
and installing firewalls to block
unsecure access along with ensuring a
robust password protection policy and
multi factor authentication, can also
help to mitigate any potential damage.
Abraham: Limiting user’s permissions
by only allowing access to files
and folders necessary for them
to do their work can also help.
A user access system can also verify
the identity of users, stopping
hackers from taking advantage of
uncontrolled administrative privileges.
This can also help to protect from
insider or social engineering attacks.
Nicole: Those with access to sensitive
or highly available data should be the
first to be identified as at risk and
this approach should then be implemented
through the system and all other users.
Abraham: And finally, the
vulnerability of employees rather
than hardware and software systems.
By training staff on how to mitigate
threats by being fully aware of what
role they play in the cyber security
of their organisation, can help to
reduce the issue of human error.
Regular training in how and why
cyber security is important can help
to develop a culture of security
across all employees, by helping
to make them all aware of potential
attack by social engineering.
Nicole: Within a business or
organisation everyone has a role
to play to make sure that cyber
security is given the importance
it deserves by making them aware of
the impact the lack of it can have.